Guide to the David Montgomery Papers TAM.446
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
David Montgomery Papers
1820-1925, 1953-2009
1960-2000
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Montgomery, David, 1927-2011
Montgomery, Ed
TAM.446
50.5 Linear Feet in 45 record cartons and 12 card boxes
700 Megabytes
David Montgomery (1927-2011) was Farnam Professor of History Emeritus at Yale University. Montgomery is considered one of the foremost academics specializing in United States labor history, and is credited as a leading founder of "new labor history" in the U.S., placing emphsis on working-class culture, rather than simply their organizations. Contains the research files, clippings correspondence, printed ephemera, typescripts, and FOIA files. Three boxes are devoted to the FBI files of Jay Lovestone, a former Communist Party USA leader who became a militant anti-communist, specializing in combating communism in labor movements in the U.S. and around the world.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers with the acception of any letters from Dana Frank to David Montgomery and the unprocessed 2017 accretion. Access to the Dana Frank letters is restricted until death. Access to the 2017 Accretion to the David Montgomery Papers is restricted until the materials have benn processed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was initially donated by David Montgomery in 2008 and 2009; additional materials were donated in 2017 by Edward B. Montgomery and Claude D. Montgomery. The accession numbers associated with these donations are 1997.024, 2008.034, 2009.069, and 2017.036.
Arrangement
Materials within the 2017 accretion have not been arranged by an archivist. Original order may have been lost during packing. The collection contains numerous photocopies of articles, and groupings of folders arranged in alphabetical order by author's last name or by article topic, in some cases, still remain.
Biographical / Historical
David Montgomery (1927-2011) was Farnam Professor of History Emeritus at Yale University. Montgomery is considered one of the foremost academics specializing in United States labor history and has written extensively on the subject. Along with David Brody and Herbert Gutman, he is credited with founding the field of "new labor history" in the U.S. Following the example of British historian E. P. Thompson, Montgomery encouraged a generation of labor historians to examine working-class culture, rather than simply their organizations. He was also President of the Organization of American Historians from 1999 to 2000.
Scope and Contents
The David Montgomery Papers document the professional career and, in some cases, the personal life of historian and professor David Montgomery (1927-2011).The bulk of the collection consists of Montgomery's research files, which mainly focus on the labor history of the United States, although some files describe labor movements that occurred in China, the United Kingdom, Canada, and Latin America. Materials include photocopies of articles, newspaper clippings, correspondence, printed ephemera, handwritten notes, typescripts, and FOIA files. Three boxes are specifically devoted to the FBI files of Jay Lovestone, a former Communist Party USA leader who became a militant anti-communist, specializing in combating communism in labor movements in the U.S. and abroad, was employed by the AFL-CIO for this purpose, and cooperated closely with U.S. government agencies. In addition to Montgomery's research files, the collection also contains a few awards, some materials related to Yale University where Montgomery taught, photographs, course materials (including student theses), medical records, personal financial documents (including tax returns), and child artwork.
Labor unions -- United States.; Working class; Labor movement.; Working class -- United States.; Labor unions; Labor movement -- United States.; Communism.; United States -- History -- Civil War -- 1861-1865; Labor -- History; Labor -- Education.; Lovestone, Jay.; Montgomery, David, 1927-2011; Montgomery, Ed; Montgomery, David, 1927-2011; Montgomery, Ed
- Research Files, 1870s, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  General
  Research Files: History of Knights of Labor in Philadelphia (manuscript, brochure), 1889-1902; History of Typographical Union, Philadelphia (manuscript, transcripts, handwritten lists), 1870s; Oral History Interview Transcripts: Edward J. Sullivan, Anna Weinstock, Samuel Angoff (labor movement, MA), 1969, 1970; Membership Applications for "Sovereigns of Industry", 1870s
  Committee to Secure Justice for Hospital Workers - establishing a union at Presbiterian-University Hospital in Pittsburgh (application cards, clippings, correspondence), 1970
- Research Files; Academic Files; Labor Activities, 1934-1936, 1996-2001 (Box 2)
  Research Files: National Steel Labor Relations Board related correspondence 1934-1935; Jones and Laughlin Case (clippings,correspondence, reports and transcripts of Proceedings before the National Labor Relations Board, exhibits of hearings) 1934-1936
  Academic Files: Teaching Related Materials (correspondence, reviews of dissertations, tenureships, and grant applications, student essays, conferences)1996-1999
  Labor Activities: Labor History (periodical) correspondence 1996-2001; Labor History Forum (blog printed from the Internet) 1996-2001
- Correspondence, Academic Documents; Typescripts by Others (Part 1), 1990s (Box 3)
  Alphabetic Files of recent correspondence and academic documents (student essays, tenureship recommendations) Manuscripts of Leslie A. Falk, Thomas Y. Fujita Rony
- Correspondence, Academic; Typescripts by Students and Others (Part 2), 1990s (Box 4)
  Academic files: correspondence, letters of supports reviews for tenureships, grants, and publications; manuscripts of papers
  manuscripts by others: African-American Railroad Labor by Eric Arnesen
- Correspondence, Academic; Typescripts by Students and Others (Part 3), 1990s (Box 5)
  Academic files: correspondence, letters of supports reviews for tenureships, grants, and publications; manuscripts of papers in alphabetic order
- Lovestone, Jay: FBI/FOIA Files (Part 1), 1953-1955 (Box 6)
  Jay Lovestone FBI/FOIA Files: Part 1
- Lovestone, Jay: FBI/FOIA Files (Part 2), 1952-1960 (Box 7)
  Jay Lovestone FBI/FOIA files: Part 2
- Lovestone, Jay: FBI/FOIA Files (Part 3), 1950-1954 (Box 8)
  Jay Loveston FBI/FOIA Files: Part 3
- Academic Files (Part 1), 1964-1980s (Box 9)
  Academic Files: student theses,grant applications, course and lecture outlines on American Industrial Workers (Warwick lectures), research materials (Douglas Papers) Correspondence: Institutional (Social Science History Association, University of Illinois Press, University of Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania Labor History Society) and Individual
- Academic Files (Part 2), ca. 1981-1984 (Box 10)
  Academic Files: Correspondence, Invidudals; International Labor and Working Class History correspondence; research materials (including articles and notes)
- Academic Files (Part 3), 1980s-1990s (Box 11)
  Academic Files: teaching at Brazil Unicamp, Oxford, Wilson Center, courses: Race and Class Seminar, Industrial Democracy at the Wilson Center, Southwest Labor Studies, 19th century Social History, International Labor and Working Class History
  Academic Files: correspondence, student essays, evaluations A-J; 1990-1992
- Writings and Correspondence, 1960s-1970s (Box 12)
  Writings (Typescripts: articles, book chapters, and related correspondence); Constance Round Table (participants papers and publications); Correspondence, Individual, K-l)
- Correspondence, General, 1970s-1990 (Box 13)
  General Correspondence, A-J; Correspondence with United Electrical Workers Archives
- Correspondence, General; Academic Files (Part 1), 1975-1977, ca. 1987-1990 (Box 14)
  Correspondence, Individuals and other Academic Institutions (ca. 1987-1990)
  Academic files: letters of supports; reviews for tenureships, grants, and publications; papers and research proposals submitted by students, course materials: American Labor in the 1880s, American Labor in the 1890s, American Social History, Popular Movements (1975-1977)
- Academic Files; Correspondence; Subject Files, late 1970s, 1980s (Box 15)
  Academic Files: Conferences on Russian Labor, Southern Labor Studies, Connecticut Workers and Techonological Change, The Future of Labore History; Colgate Teachers' Institute, Canadian Historical Associations
  Correspondence: A-B, Academia Related Publications: Labor History, International Review of Social History
  Subject Files: Detroit Labor History Tours, Hungarian-American Exchange, Strikes Roundtable, Workers' World Exhibit
- Correspondence, General; Academic Files (Part 2), ca. 1989-1994 (Box 16)
  Correspondence: Individuals and other Academic Institutions
  Academic files (alphabetical order: K-Z): clippings, letters of supports, reviews for tenureships, grants, and publications; papers and research proposals submitted by students
- Correspondence, General; Academic Files (Part 3), 1980s (Box 17)
  Academic files (alphabetical order: M-Z): clippings, letters of supports, reviews for tenureships, grants, and publications; papers and research proposals submitted by students, conference in Paris: Socialism in the US, papers
  Other Institution: Institutio Socialista, Labor History
- Academic Files (University of Warwick); Writings; Political Activities, 1970s-1990s (Box 18)
  Academic Files: University of Warwick courses (include syllabuses, bibliographies)on Labor History, Social History, Industrialization and Popular Movements;PhD reading lists, MA theses; essays by Tatsuro Nomura,manuscripts on steelworkers Other Activities: Pittsburgh Committee to Defend POlitical Freedom, Organization of American Historians, J.P. Stevens workers
- Academic Files (Part 4), 1970s-1980s (Box 19)
  Academic Files: Yale Ethnic Courses Committee, Hispanic History Search, labor bibliographies, grant applications, correspondence, conferences (Paris, Milan) course outlines and notes: social history, industrialization and popular movements,civil war Files on other organizations: Pittsburgh Professioanl Union, Women's Committee
- Correspondence, General; Academic Files; Research Files, 1970s-2000 (Box 20)
  Correspondence: Individual, Alphabetic order: Q-Z, 1976-1980 Academic Files: Japanese Fellowship, Basso Foundation, Temple University Press, McKinzie Symposium Research Files: Journal of American History, Organization of American Historians
- Academic Files (Part 5), 1920s-1930s; 1960s-1980s (Box 21)
  Academic Files: course documents: Black History, US Social and Economic History, US Colonial History, Working Class History, Immigration; conference papers Research Files: Workers Education 1920s-1930s, Socialist History 1600-1873 Institutional Correspondence: Rutgers-Princeton-Suny Binghampton, Yale, ILWCH, Ethnic Institutions
- Correspondence, General; Writings, 1970s-1980s (Box 22)
  Correspondence, Academic and Research Related: Alphabetical
  Writings by David Montgomery: "Challenges Facing Historians of the Working Class" "William H. Sylvis," "Strikes of Machinists in the United States, 1870-1922" and other manuscripts on Montgomery Strikes
  Biographical Files: Curriculum Vitaes
- Correspondence, General; Academic Files, ca. 1978-1982 (Box 23)
  Correspondence: Academic and Research Related, Alphabetical
  Academic Files: grant applications, letters of recommendations, manuscripts by colleagues and students